Bruno Giussani: Commissioner, thank you for coming to TED.
برونز خيوساني: شكرًا لحضورك إلى TED سيدي المفوض
António Guterres: Pleasure.
أنطونيو غيتراس: يشرفني ذلك.
BG: Let's start with a figure.
برونز خيوساني: دعنا نبدأ برقم.
During 2015, almost one million refugees and migrants arrived in Europe
خلال 2015، وصل إلى أوروبا قرابة المليون لاجئ ومهاجر
from many different countries,
من عدة دول،
of course, from Syria and Iraq, but also from Afghanistan
بالطبع من سوريا والعراق ومن أفغانستان أيضا
and Bangladesh and Eritrea and elsewhere.
وبنجلاديش وأريتريا وأماكن أخرى.
And there have been reactions of two different kinds:
وكانت هناك ردود فعل من نوعين مختلفين:
welcoming parties and border fences.
حفلات استقبال وحواجز حدودية.
But I want to look at it a little bit
أريد أن أنظر في هذا الموضوع أكثر
from the short-term and the long-term perspective.
على المدى القصير والمنظور طويل الأجل.
And the first question is very simple:
والسؤال الأول بسيط للغاية :
Why has the movement of refugees spiked so fast in the last six months?
لماذا كانت حركة اللاجئين شائكة خلال الستة أشهر الأخيرة ؟
AG: Well, I think, basically, what triggered this huge increase
أنطونيو غيتراس: حسنا، أعتقد، في الأساس، أن سبب هذه الزيادة الضخمة
was the Syrian refugee group.
هي مجموعات اللاجئين السوريين.
There has been an increased movement into Europe from Africa, from Asia,
فقد زاد التحاقهم بأروربا من إفريقيا وآسيا،
but slowly growing, and all of a sudden we had this massive increase
ولكن يرتفع عددهم ببطء، وفجأة أصبح لدينا هذه الزيادة الهائلة
in the first months of this year.
في بداية الأشهر الستة الأولى من السنة.
Why? I think there are three reasons,
لماذا؟ أعتقد يوجد ثلاثة أسباب،
two long-term ones and the trigger.
اثنان منها على المدى الطويل وهي السبب.
The long-term ones, in relation to Syrians,
على المدى الطويل ترتبط بالسوريين،
is that hope is less and less clear for people.
غير أن الأمل يقل ويقل وهو واضح للناس .
I mean, they look at their own country
أعني، أنهم ينظرون إلى بلدهم
and they don't see much hope to go back home,
ولا يرون أمل كبير للعودة الى بلادهم،
because there is no political solution,
لأنه لا يوجد حلّ سياسي،
so there is no light at the end of the tunnel.
لذلك فليس هناك بصيص من الأمل في ذلك النفق المظلم .
Second, the living conditions
ثانيا، ظروف العيش
of the Syrians in the neighboring countries have been deteriorating.
للسوريين في الدول المجاورة متدهورة.
We just had research with the World Bank,
في بحث مع البنك الدولي،
and 87 percent of the Syrians in Jordan
87 % من السوريين في الأردن
and 93 percent of the Syrians in Lebanon
93 % من السوريين في لبنان
live below the national poverty lines.
يعيشون تحت خط الفقر.
Only half of the children go to school,
فقط النصف من الأطفال يذهبون للمدارس،
which means that people are living very badly.
ما يعني أنهم يعيشون معيشة مضنية.
Not only are they refugees, out of home,
ليس فقط لاجئين خرجوا من بلادهم،
not only have they suffered what they have suffered,
ليس فقط عانوا ما عانوه،
but they are living in very, very dramatic conditions.
ولكنهم أيضا يعانون من ظروف دراماتيكية.
And then the trigger was when all of a sudden,
ثم السبب عندما فوجئ الجميع،
international aid decreased.
بانخفاض المساعدات الدولية.
The World Food Programme was forced, for lack of resources,
اضطر برنامج الأغذية العالمي، بسبب نقص الموارد،
to cut by 30 percent food support to the Syrian refugees.
إلى استقطاع 30% من الطعام الموجه للاجئين السوريين.
They're not allowed to work,
لم يكن يسمح لهم بالعمل،
so they are totally dependent on international support,
لذا فهم يعتمدون اعتمادا كليا على الدعم الدولي،
and they felt, "The world is abandoning us."
وشعروا بأن " العالم يتخلّى عنا."
And that, in my opinion, was the trigger.
وكان هذا على ما أعتقد السبب.
All of a sudden, there was a rush,
وفجأة كان هناك تسارع في الحركة،
and people started to move in large numbers
وبدأ الناس في التحرك بأعداد كبيرة
and, to be absolutely honest,
ولكي أكون صادقا تماما،
if I had been in the same situation
لوكنت في نفس الموقف
and I would have been brave enough to do it,
لكانت لدي الشجاعة الكافية للقيام بذلك،
I think I would have done the same.
لقمت به.
BG: But I think what surprised many people is it's not only sudden,
برونز خيوساني: ولكن أعتقد أن ما أدهش العديد من الناس ليست المفاجأة،
but it wasn't supposed to be sudden.
ولكن لم يكن من المفترض ان تكون مفاجأة.
The war in Syria has been happening for five years.
الحرب في سوريا قائمة منذ خمس سنوات.
Millions of refugees are in camps and villages and towns around Syria.
ملايين من اللاجئين في معسكرات وقرى ومدن حول سورية.
You have yourself warned about the situation
كنت قد أخذت حذرك بنفسك من الموقف
and about the consequences of a breakdown of Libya, for example,
وعن العواقب بسقوط ليبيا على سبيل المثال،
and yet Europe looked totally unprepared.
ومع ذلك يبدو أن أوروبا لم تكن مستعدة تماما.
AG: Well, unprepared because divided,
أنطونيو غيتراس: غير مستعدة لأنها منقسمة،
and when you are divided, you don't want to recognize the reality.
وعندما يكون هناك انقسامات، فأنت لا تدرك الواقع.
You prefer to postpone decisions,
تفضّل أن تؤجل قراراتك،
because you do not have the capacity to make them.
لأنك لا تملك القدرة لأخذها.
And the proof is that even when the spike occurred,
والدليل على ذلك، حتى عند حدوث الأزمة،
Europe remained divided
بقيت أوروبا منقسمة
and was unable to put in place a mechanism to manage the situation.
ولم تكن قادرة على وضع آليّة لإدارة الوضعية.
You talk about one million people.
أنت تتحدّث عن مليون شخص.
It looks enormous,
يبدو العدد ضخما،
but the population of the European Union is 550 million people,
ولكن يبلغ عدد سكان الاتحاد الأوروبي قرابة 550 مليون شخص،
which means we are talking about one per every [550] Europeans.
مما يعني أننا نتحدث عن شخص على 2000 شخص أوروبي.
Now, in Lebanon, we have one refugee per three Lebanese.
حاليا، في لبنان، لدينا لاجئ لكلّ ثلاثة لبنانيين.
And Lebanon? Struggling, of course, but it's managing.
ولبنان؟ بالطبع هي تعاني، ولكنّها تستطيع التعامل مع ذلك.
So, the question is: is this something that could have been managed
إذن، السؤال هو: هل هذه وضعية يمكن إدارتها
if -- not mentioning the most important thing,
لو -- من دون ذكر الشيء المهم جدّا،
which would have been addressing the root causes,
والذي من الممكن أن يعالج الأسباب الجذريّة،
but forgetting about root causes for now,
ولكن فلننسى الأسباب الجذريّة،
looking at the phenomenon as it is --
فلننظر إلى الحالة كما هي --
if Europe were able to come together in solidarity
لو اتحدت البلدان الأوروبية مع بعضها
to create an adequate reception capacity of entry points?
لخلق نقاط دخول اللاجئين ذات قدرة كافية لاستقبالهم؟
But for that, the countries at entry points need to be massively supported,
ولكن من أجل ذلك، البلدان التي تمتلك نقاط دخول في حاجة إلى دعم كبير،
and then screening the people with security checks
ومن ثم تنقية الشعب باستخدام عمليات التفتيش الأمنية
and all the other mechanisms,
وكل الآليات الأخرى،
distributing those that are coming into all European countries,
وتوزيع أولئك القادمين من مختلف البلدان على البلدان الأوروبية،
according to the possibilities of each country.
حسب طاقة استيعاب كل بلد.
I mean, if you look at the relocation program
أعني إذا تأملت برنامج الترحيل
that was approved by the Commission, always too little too late,
الذي تم الاتفاق عليه من قبل اللجنة، في أغلب الحالات بعد فوات الأوان،
or by the Council, too little too late --
أو من قبل المجلس، في أغلب الحالات بعد فوات الأوان --
BG: It's already breaking down.
برونز خيوساني: نحن الآن في حالة من التحطّم.
AG: My country is supposed to receive four thousand.
أنطونيو غتيراس: من المفترض أن تستقبل بلادي 4 ألاف.
Four thousand in Portugal means nothing.
4 ألاف بالبرتغال لا تعني شيئا.
So this is perfectly manageable if it is managed,
إذن يمكن التعامل مع ذلك في حالة تمت إدارته،
but in the present circumstances, the pressure is at the point of entry,
ولكن حاليا في ظل هذه الظروف الراهنة، تشهد نقاط الدخول ضغطا،
and then, as people move in this chaotic way through the Balkans,
وبعد ذلك، ينتقل الأشخاص بطريقة فوضوية من خلال البلقان،
then they come to Germany, Sweden, basically, and Austria.
ثم يذهبون بالاساس إلى ألمانيا، السويد والنمسا.
They are the three countries that are, in the end, receiving the refugees.
هذه البلدان الثلاثة هي التي تستقبل اللاجئين.
The rest of Europe is looking without doing much.
وباقي الدول الأوروبية تتأمل الوضع من دون القيام بشيء.
BG: Let me try to bring up three questions,
برونز خيوساني: افسح لي المجال لطرح ثلاثة أسئلة،
playing a bit devil's advocate.
فألعب دور المحامي الشرير.
I'll try to ask them, make them blunt.
سأحاول طرحها، وجعلها حادّة.
But I think the questions are very present
ولكن أعتقد بأن هذه الأسئلة موجودة
in the minds of many people in Europe right now,
في عقول الكثير من الأشخاص بأوروبا الآن،
The first, of course, is about numbers.
أول سؤال، بالطبع، حول الأرقام.
You say 550 million versus one million is not much, but realistically,
تقولون 550 مليون مقابل مليون ليس بالكثير ولكن في الحقيقة،
how many people can Europe take?
كم عدد الناس الذين تستطيع أوروبا استقبالهم؟
AG: Well, that is a question that has no answer,
أنطونيو غيتراس: حسنا، هذا سؤال بدون إجابة،
because refugees have the right to be protected.
لأنه لدى اللاجئين الحق في الحماية.
And there is such a thing as international law,
وهناك ما يسمّى بالقانون الدولي،
so there is no way you can say, "I take 10,000 and that's finished."
لذا لا مجال لقول "سأستقبل فقط 10000 وانتهى الأمر."
I remind you of one thing:
أذكركم بشيء:
in Turkey, at the beginning of the crisis, I remember one minister saying,
في تركيا، خلال المرحلة الأولى من الأزمة أتذكر أحد الوزراء الذي قال،
"Turkey will be able to receive up to 100,000 people."
"سوف تستقبل تركيا 10000 شخص فقط".
Turkey has now two million three-hundred thousand
ولكن تحتوي تركيا حاليا على ما يقارب 2مليون و300 ألف شخص
or something of the sort, if you count all refugees.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل، إذا قمت بحساب عدد اللاجئين.
So I don't think it's fair to say how many we can take.
لذا أعتقد أنه ليس من المنصف أن نُحدد عدد الأشخاص الذين يتم استقبالهم.
What it is fair to say is: how we can we organize ourselves
ولكن من العدل أن نقول: كيف يمكن أن ننظم أنفسنا
to assume our international responsibilities?
لنحتمل مسؤولياتنا الدوليّة؟
And Europe has not been able to do so,
ولكن أوروبا لم تعد قادرة على القيام بذلك،
because basically, Europe is divided because there is no solidarity
لأن أوروبا أساسا منقسمة وذلك لانعدام التضامن
in the European project.
خلال المشروع الأوروبي.
And it's not only about refugees; there are many other areas.
وليس فقط بما يتعلق باللاجئين، ولكن العديد من المجالات الأخرى.
And let's be honest, this is the moment in which we need more Europe
ولنكن صريحين، هذا هو الوقت الذي نحتاج فيه إلى أوروبا
instead of less Europe.
أكثر من ذي قبل.
But as the public less and less believes in European institutions,
ولكن بما أن المجتمع أصبح يُؤمن أقل بالمؤسسات الأوروبية،
it is also each time more difficult to convince the public
أصبح من الصعب إقناع المجتمع
that we need more Europe to solve these problems.
بحاجتنا الملحة لأوروبا لحلّ هذه المشاكل.
BG: We seem to be at the point
برونز خيوساني: يبدو أننا في وضع
where the numbers turn into political shifts, particularly domestically.
حيث تتحول الأرقام إلى نوبات سياسية ولا سيما على الصعيد المحلي.
We saw it again this weekend in France,
لقد شاهدنا هذا مجددا في نهاية الأسبوع في فرنسا،
but we have seen it over and over in many countries:
ولكن شاهدناه مرارا وتكرارا في عديد البلدان:
in Poland and in Denmark and in Switzerland and elsewhere,
في بولندا والدنمارك وفي سويسرا وغيرها،
where the mood changes radically because of the numbers,
حيث يتغير المزاج جذريا بسبب الأرقام،
although they are not very significant in absolute numbers.
بالرغم من عدم أهميتها كأرقام.
The Prime Minister of --
رئيس الوزراء --
AG: But, if I may, on these:
أنطونيو غيتراس: ولكن، إن سمحت لي، في هذا الموضوع:
I mean, what does a European see at home
أعني، ما الذي يراه الأوروبيون في منزل
in a village where there are no migrants?
في قرية لا يوجد بها مهاجرون؟
What a European sees is, on television,
ما يراه الأوروبي في التلفاز،
every single day, a few months ago, opening the news every single day,
كلّ يوم، منذ عدة أشهر، عندما يشاهد نشرة الأخبار كل يوم،
a crowd coming, uncontrolled,
هو حشد من الأشخاص يأتون ولا يتمّ ضبطهم،
moving from border to border,
يتنقلون بين الحدود،
and the images on television were of hundreds
وكانت مئات أو آلاف الصور
or thousands of people moving.
للناس الذين يتنقلون.
And the idea is that nobody is taking care of it --
والفكرة هنا أنه لا أحد يعطي أهمية لذلك --
this is happening without any kind of management.
هذا يحصل من دون القيام بأي نوع من إدارة الوضع
And so their idea was, "They are coming to my village."
وكانت الفكرة، "إنهم آتون إلى قريتي."
So there was this completely false idea that Europe was being invaded
لذا كانت هناك تلك الفكرة المغالطة بأنه سيتم اجتياح أوروبا
and our way of life is going to change, and everything will --
وستتغير طريقة عيشنا وكلّ شيء --
And the problem is that if this had been properly managed,
والمشكلة أنه لو تمّت إدارة هذه القضية بطريقة جيدة،
if people had been properly received,
لو تم استقبال الناس بطريقة ملائمة،
welcomed, sheltered at point of entry, screened at point of entry,
الترحيب بهم في نقطة الدخول، وتنقيتهم،
and the moved by plane to different European countries,
وثم ترحيلهم بالطائرة إلى مختلف البلدان الأوروبية،
this would not have scared people.
لم يكن ليخيف هذا الناس.
But, unfortunately, we have a lot of people scared,
ولكن للأسف، يشعر الكثير من الأشخاص بالرعب،
just because Europe was not able to do the job properly.
فقط لأن أوروبا لم تكن قادرة على القيام بهذه المهمة بشكل صحيح.
BG: But there are villages in Germany
برونزخيوساني: ولكن توجد مجموعة من القرى بألمانيا
with 300 inhabitants and 1,000 refugees.
تحتوي على 300 ساكن و1000 لاجئ.
So, what's your position?
إذن، ماهو موقفكم؟
How do you imagine these people reacting?
وكيف تتخيل ردة فعل هؤلاء الأشخاص؟
AG: If there would be a proper management of the situation
أنطونيو غيتراس: إذا تمت إدارة الوضع بطريقة صحيحة
and the proper distribution of people all over Europe,
وتم توزيع اللاجئين على أوروبا،
you would always have the percentage that I mentioned:
ستحصل دائما على النسبة المئوية التي ذكرتها سابقا:
one per each 2,000.
لاجئ لكل 2000 ساكن.
It is because things are not properly managed
بسبب عدم إدارة الوضعية بطريقة صحيحة
that in the end we have situations
نتحصل في نهاية المطاف على وضعيات
that are totally impossible to live with, and of course if you have a village --
من المستحيل العيش معها، وبالطبع إن كانت لديك قرية --
in Lebanon, there are many villages
بلبنان، هناك العديد من القرى
that have more Syrians than Lebanese; Lebanon has been living with that.
حيث يفوق عدد السكان السوريين عدد السكان اللبنانيين ولقد تعايشت لبنان
I'm not asking for the same to happen in Europe,
مع هذه الوضعية. أنا لا أطلب أن يحصل المثل بأوروبا
for all European villages to have more refugees than inhabitants.
بأن تحتوي القرى الأوروبية على لاجئين أكثر من ساكني المنطقة.
What I am asking is for Europe to do the job properly,
ما أطلبه هو أن تقوم أوروبا بدورها على أحسن وجه،
and to be able to organize itself to receive people
وأن تكون قادرة على التنظيم لاستقبال الأشخاص
as other countries in the world were forced to do in the past.
مثلما تم إجبار البلدان الأخرى على القيام بذلك في الماضي.
BG: So, if you look at the global situation not only at Europe --
برونز خيوساني: إذن، إذا نظرت إلى الوضعية عامة وليس فقط في أوروبا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BG: Yes!
برونز خيوساني: نعم !
BG: If you look at the global situation, so, not only at Europe,
برونز خيوساني: إذن، إذا نظرت إلى الوضعية عامة وليس فقط في أوروبا --
I know you can make a long list of countries
أعرف يمكنك ذكر لائحة طويلة من البلدان
that are not really stepping up,
التي لا تقدم يد المساعدة حقا،
but I'm more interested in the other part --
ولكنني مهتم أكثر بالجزء الآخر --
is there somebody who's doing the right thing?
هل هناك من يقوم بما هو صحيح؟
AG: Well, 86 percent of the refugees in the world
أنطونيو غتيراس: حسنا، 86% من اللاجئين بالعالم
are in the developing world.
هم بالبلدان النامية.
And if you look at countries like Ethiopia --
وإذا نظرت إلى بلدان مثل اثيوبيا --
Ethiopia has received more than 600,000 refugees.
لقد قامت اثيوبيا باستقبال ما يعادل أكثر من 600.000 لاجئ.
All the borders in Ethiopia are open.
كل الحدود لاثيوبيا مفتوحة.
And they have, as a policy,
ولديهم، كسياسة،
they call the "people to people" policy that every refugee should be received.
ما يسمونها سياسة "الناس للناس" التي ينبغي أن يتلقاها كل لاجئ.
And they have South Sudanese,
ولديهم لاجؤون من جنوب السودان،
they have Sudanese, they have Somalis.
ولديهم السودانيون والصوماليون.
They have all the neighbors.
لديهم كل الجيران.
They have Eritreans.
لديهم الإريتريين.
And, in general,
وعامة،
African countries are extremely welcoming of refugees coming,
ترحب الدول الإفريقية باللاجئين،
and I would say that in the Middle East
وأود أن أقول بأنه في الشرق الأوسط
and in Asia, we have seen a tendency for borders to be open.
وآسيا لاحظنا الميل إلى فتح الحدود.
Now we see some problems with the Syrian situation,
حاليا نلاحظ بعض المشاكل مع الوضع السوري،
as the Syrian situation evolved into also a major security crisis,
مع تطور الوضع السوري إلى أزمة أمنية كبيرة،
but the truth is that for a large period,
ولكن في الحقيقة لمدة كبيرة،
all borders in the Middle East were open.
كانت كل الحدود بالشرق الأوسط مفتوحة.
The truth is that for Afghans,
الحقيقة هي أنه بالنسبة للأفغان،
the borders of Pakistan and Iran were open for, at the time,
كانت حدود الباكستان وإيران مفتوحة لهم في ذلك الوقت،
six million Afghans that came.
حيث أتى 6 ملايين أفغاني.
So I would say that even today, the trend in the developing world
إذن أود القول أنه حتى اليوم، تتجه البلدان النامية
has been for borders to be open.
إلى فتح الحدود.
The trend in the developed world is for these questions to become
الاتجاه السائد في العالم المتقدم هو بخصوص هذه الأسئلة
more and more complex,
لكي تكون أكثر وأكثر تعقيدا،
especially when there is, in the public opinion,
خاصة عندما تكون هناك، في الرأي العام،
a mixture of discussions between refugee protections on one side
مزيج من المناقشات بين حماية اللاجئين من جهة
and security questions -- in my opinion, misinterpreted -- on the other side.
وأسئلة الحماية -- في رأيي يُساء تفسيرها-- من جهة أخرى.
BG: We'll come back to that too,
برونز خيوساني: سوف نعود إلى هذا الموضوع أيضا،
but you mentioned the cutting of funding and the vouchers
ولكنك ذكرت وقف التمويل ومستندات الصرف
from the World Food Programme.
من برنامج الأغذية العالمي.
That reflects the general underfunding of the organizations
وهو ما يعكس نقص التمويل العام للمنظمات
working on these issues.
العاملة على هذه القضايا.
Now that the world seems to have woken up,
حاليا حيث يبدو أن العالم قد استيقظ،
are you getting more funding and more support,
هل تحصلون على المزيد من التمويل والدعم،
or it's still the same?
أو هل بقي الأمر على ماهو عليه؟
AG: We are getting more support.
أنطونيو غيتراس: نحن نحصل على مزيد من الدعم.
I would say that we are coming close to the levels of last year.
أودّ أن أقول بأننا نقترب من مستويات العام الماضي.
We were much worse during the summer.
كنا أسوء بكثير خلال الصيف.
But that is clearly insufficient to address the needs of the people
ولكن يبدو واضحا أن هذا غير كاف لمعالجة حاجيات الأشخاص
and address the needs of the countries
وحاجيات البلدان
that are supporting the people.
الداعمة لهؤلاء الأشخاص.
And here we have a basic review of the criteria, the objectives,
وهنا لدينا تلخيص أساسي للمعايير والأهداف،
the priorities of development cooperation that is required.
وأولويات التنمية المشتركة المطلوبة.
For instance, Lebanon and Jordan are middle-income countries.
على سبيل المثال، لبنان والأردن هي بلدان متوسطة الدخل.
Because they are middle-income countries,
ولأنهم بلدان متوسطة الدخل،
they cannot receive soft loans or grants from the World Bank.
لا يمكنهم الحصول على قروض ميسرة أو منح من البنك الدولي.
Now, today this doesn't make any sense,
حاليا، هذا لا يشكل أي معنى،
because they are providing a global public good.
لأنهم يوفرون المصلحة العامة العالميّة.
They have millions of refugees there,
لديهم الملايين من اللاجئين هناك،
and to be honest, they are pillars of stability in the region,
ولنكن صادقين، هم دعائم الاستقرار بالمنطقة،
with all the difficulties they face,
مع كل الصعوبات التي واجهوها،
and the first line of defense of our collective security.
وخط الدفاع الأول لأمننا الجماعي.
So it doesn't make sense
إذن أن لا تكون تلك الدول من الأولويات
that these countries are not a first priority
هذا لا يشكل أي معنى
in development cooperation policies.
في سياسات التعاون الإنمائي.
And they are not.
وهي ليست كذلك.
And not only do the refugees live in very dramatic circumstances
وليس اللاجئون فقط من يعيشون في ظروف دراماتيكيّة
inside those countries,
داخل تلك البلدان،
but the local communities themselves are suffering,
ولكن المجتمعات المحليّة نفسها تعاني،
because salaries went down,
بسبب انخفاض الرواتب،
because there are more unemployed,
لارتفاع عدد الأشخاص العاطلين عن العمل،
because prices and rents went up.
بسبب ارتفاع الأسعار والإيجار.
And, of course, if you look at today's situation
وبالطبع إذا تأملت الوضعية اليوم
of the indicators in these countries,
للمؤشرات في هذه البلدان،
it is clear that, especially their poor groups of the population,
فهي واضحة تماما، وخاصة تلك الفئات الضعيفة،
are living worse and worse because of the crisis they are facing.
فهم يعيشون في ظروف أسوء كل مرّة بسبب الأزمة التي يواجهونها.
BG: Who should be providing this support?
برونز خيوساني: من الذي ينبغي أن يوفّر الدعم؟
Country by country, international organizations, the European Union?
كلّ بلد، المنظمات الدولية، الاتحاد الأوروبي؟
Who should be coming up with this support?
من ينبغي أن يقدّم الدعم؟
AG: We need to join all efforts.
أنطونيو غتراس: يجب أن تتضافر كل جهودنا.
It's clear that bilateral cooperation is essential.
من الواضح أن التعاون الثنائي أساسي.
It's clear that multilateral
من الواضح أن التعاون متعدد الأطراف مطلوب.
It's clear that international financial institutions should have flexibility
من الواضح أنه على المؤسسات المالية الدولية أن تكون أكثر مرونة
in order to be able to invest more massively
لكي تكون قادرة على الاستثمار على نطاق أوسع
in support to these countries.
دعما لهذه البلدان.
We need to combine all the instruments and to understand that today,
نحن في حاجة إلى جمع كل التجهيزات ولفهم ذلك اليوم،
in protracted situations, at a certain moment,
خلال الوضعيات طويلة الأمد، في لحظة معينة،
that it doesn't make sense anymore to make a distinction
التي لا تشكل أي معنى للتمييز
between humanitarian aid and development aid
بين المساعدات الإنسانية والمساعدات التنموية
or development processes.
أو عمليات التنمية.
Because you are talking about children in school,
لأنك تتحدث عن أطفال بالمدرسة،
you are talking about health,
تتحدث عن الصحة،
you are talking about infrastructure that is overcrowded.
تتحدّث عن البنية التحتية المكتظة
You are talking about things that require a long-term perspective,
تتحدث عن أشياء تتطلب رسم منظوري طويل الأمد،
a development perspective
رسم منظوري تنموي
and not only an emergency humanitarian aid perspective.
وليس فقط رسم منظوري للمساعدات الإنسانية في حالات الطوارئ.
BG: I would like your comment on something
برونز خيوساني: أريد منك أن تُعلّق على شيء
that was in newspapers this morning.
نُشر بالصحف هذا الصباح.
It is a statement made by the current front-runner
هو بيان أدلى به المرشّح الأساسي الحالي
for the Republican nomination for US President, Donald Trump.
لرئاسة الحزب الجمهوري الأمريكي، دونالد ترامب.
Yesterday, he said this.
قال هذا البارحة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No, listen to this. It's interesting.
لا. استمعوا إلى هذا. هذا مثير للاهتمام.
I quote: "I am calling for a total and complete shutdown
أقتبس: "أنا أدعو إلى إيقاف كلّي
of Muslims entering the US,
لدخول المسلمين للولايات المتحدة،
until our country's representatives can figure out what's going on."
إلى أن يكتشف ممثلي البلاد ما الذي يجري."
How do you react to that?
كيف تتفاعل مع هذا؟
AG: Well, it's not only Donald Trump.
أنطونيو غيتراس: في الحقيقة، ليس دونالد ترامب فقط.
We have seen several people around the world
لقد رأينا العديد من الناس حول العالم
with political responsibility saying, for instance,
ذوي مسؤولية سياسية يقولون، مثلا،
that Muslims refugees should not be received.
لا ينبغي قبول اللاجئين المسلمين.
And the reason why they say this
والسبب وراء قولهم هذا
is because they think that by doing or saying this,
أنهم يعتقدون بالقيام بهذا أو قول هذا،
they are protecting the security of their countries.
هم يحمون أمن بلدانهم.
Now, I've been in government.
حاليا، لقد كنت بالحكومة.
I am very keen on the need for governments
أنا حريص جدا على أن تقوم الحكومات
to protect the security of their countries
بحماية أمن بلدانهم
and their people.
وشعوبهم.
But if you say, like that,
ولكن إن قلت مثل هذا الكلام،
in the US or in any European country,
بالولايات المتحدة أو أي بلد أوروبي،
"We are going to close our doors to Muslim refugees,"
"سنقفل أبوابنا على اللاجئين المسلمين،"
what you are saying is the best possible help
ما تقوله هو أفضل اقتراح للمساعدة
for the propaganda of terrorist organizations.
على الدعاية للمنظمات الإرهابية.
Because what you are saying --
لأن ما تقوله --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
What you are saying will be heard by all the Muslims in your own country,
لأن ما تقوله سيتم سماعه من قبل المسلمين ببلدك،
and it will pave the way for the recruitment
وسيمهّد الطريق للتوظيف
and the mechanisms that, through technology,
والآليات التي من خلال التكنولوجيا،
Daesh and al-Nusra, al-Qaeda, and all those other groups
ستسمح لداعش وآل النصرة والقاعدة وكل المجموعات الأخرى
are today penetrating in our societies.
باجتياح مجتمعاتنا اليوم.
And it's just telling them, "You are right, we are against you."
وأن نقول لهم، "أنتم على حق، نحن ضدكم."
So obviously, this is creating in societies that are all multiethnic,
إذن من الواضح، أن هذا يُخلق في المجتمعات متعددة الأعراق،
multi-religious, multicultural,
متعددة الأديان والثقافات،
this is creating a situation in which, really,
هذا يخلق نوع من القضية، حقا،
it is much easier for the propaganda of these terrorist organizations
إنه من السهل الدعوة لهذه المنظمات الإرهابية
to be effective in recruiting people for terror acts
لتكون فعّالة في توظيف الأشخاص لأعمال إرهابية
within the countries where these kinds of sentences are expressed.
داخل البلدان حيث توجد مثل هذه العبارات.
BG: Have the recent attacks in Paris and the reactions to them
برونز خوساني: هل جعلت الهجمات الأخيرة بباريس وردود الفعل عليها
made your job more difficult?
عملك أصعب؟
AG: Undoubtedly.
أنطونيو غيتراس: مما لا شك فيه.
BG: In what sense?
برونز خيوساني: بأي معنى؟
AG: In the sense that, I mean, for many people the first reaction
أنطونيو غيتراس:بمعنى، أعني، كانت ردة الفعل الأولى للعديد من الأشخاص
in relation to these kinds of terrorist attacks is: close all borders --
في ما يخصّ مثل الهجمات الإرهابية : غلق كل الحدود--
not understanding that the terrorist problem in Europe is largely homegrown.
لم يفهموا أن القضية الإرهابية في أوروبا هي محليّة بشكل كبير.
We have thousands and thousands of European fighters in Syria and in Iraq,
لدينا الآلاف والآلاف من المقاتلين الأوروبيين بسوريا والعراق،
so this is not something that you solve by just not allowing Syrians to come in.
إذن لا يتم حلّ هذه القضة بمجرد منع السوريين من الدخول.
And I must say, I am convinced
ويجب أن أقول، أنا مقتنع
that the passport that appeared,
بأن جواز السفر الذي ظهر،
I believe, was put by the person who has blown --
أنا مقتنع بأنه تم وضعه من قبل الشخص الذي فجّر نفسه --
BG: -- himself up, yeah.
برونز خيوساني: نفسه، نعم.
AG: [I believe] it was on purpose,
أنطونيو غيتراس: [أعتقد] أنه كان متعمدا،
because part of the strategies of Daesh is against refugees,
لأنه جزء من استراتيجيات داعش ضد اللاجئين،
because they see refugees as people that should be with the caliphate
لأنهم يعتبرون اللاجئين كأشخاص يجب أن يكونوا مع الخلافة
and are fleeing to the crusaders.
ويهربون للصليبيين.
And I think that is part of Daesh's strategy to make Europe react,
وأعتقد هذا جزء من استراتيجية داعش بأن تجعل أوروبا تتفاعل،
closing its doors to Muslim refugees
إغلاق أبوابها وصدّ اللاجئين المسلمين
and having an hostility towards Muslims inside Europe,
وكرههم وخلق أعداء تجاه المسلمين في أوروبا،
exactly to facilitate Daesh's work.
بالضبط لتسهيل عمل داعش.
And my deep belief is that it was not the refugee movement
وأنا أؤمن كليّا بأنه ليست حركة اللاجئين
that triggered terrorism.
هي من تسببت في الإرهاب.
I think, as I said,
أعتقد، كما قلت،
essentially terrorism in Europe is today a homegrown movement
اليوم، الإرهاب أساسا في أوروبا هو حركة داخلية
in relation to the global situation that we are facing,
متعلّق بالوضع العالمي الذي نواجهه،
and what we need is exactly to prove these groups wrong,
وما الذي نحتاجه بالضبط هو إثبات أن هذه المجموعات خاطئة،
by welcoming and integrating effectively
من خلال الترحيب بالآتين من هذا الجزء من العالم
those that are coming from that part of the world.
ودمجهم بطريقة فاعلة.
And another thing that I believe is that to a large extent,
وشيء آخر أؤمن به هو، إلى حد كبير،
what we are today paying for in Europe
نحن ندفع ثمن الخسارات المتعلقة
is the failures of integration models
بنماذج التكامل في أوروبا
that didn't work in the '60s, in the '70s, in the '80s,
التي لم تنجح خلال الستينات والسبعينات والثمانينات،
in relation to big migration flows that took place at that time
ذات صلة بالتدفقات كبيرة الحجم للمهاجرين في تلك الفترة
and generated what is today in many of the people, for instance,
وتسببت في ما حصل للعديد من الأشخاص اليوم، على سبيل المثال،
of the second generation of communities,
تشعر مجتمعات الجيل الثاني،
a situation of feeling marginalized,
بالتهميش،
having no jobs,
من دون عمل،
having improper education,
تعليم غير لائق،
living in some of the neighborhoods that are not adequately provided
العيش في بعض الأحياء التي لم يتم فيها
by public infrastructure.
توفير بنية تحتية ملائمة.
And this kind of uneasiness, sometimes even anger,
وهذا النوع من عدم الارتياح، في بعض الأحيان غضب،
that exists in this second generation
الموجود عند الجيل الثاني
is largely due to the failure of integration policies,
عادة ما يكون نتيجة فشل سياسات الدمج،
to the failure of what should have been a much stronger investment
إلى الفشل في ما كان ينبغي أن يكون استثمارا أقوى بكثير
in creating the conditions for people to live together and respect each other.
في تهيئة ظروف للأشخاص للعيش معا واحترام بعضهم البعض.
For me it is clear.
بالنسبة لي هذا واضح.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
For me it is clear that all societies will be multiethnic, multicultural,
بالنسبة لي من الواضح بأن كل المجتمعات ستكون متعددة الأعراق والثقافات،
multi-religious in the future.
ومتعددة الديانات في المستقبل.
To try to avoid it is, in my opinion, impossible.
محاولة تجنب ذلك في رأيي، مستحيل.
And for me it's a good thing that they will be like that,
وبالنسبة لي، أن تصبح المجتمعات على تلك الحال شيء جيد،
but I also recognize that, for that to work properly,
ولكنني أعترف لكي يعمل ذلك بشكل صحيح،
you need a huge investment
أنتم في حاجة الى استثمارات ضخمة
in the social cohesion of your own societies.
في ما يتعلق بالتماسك الاجتماعي داخل مجتمعاتكم.
And Europe, to a large extent, failed in that investment
وفشلت أوروبا إلى حد كبير في ذلك الاستثمار
in the past few decades.
خلال العقود القليلة الماضية.
BG: Question: You are stepping down from your job at the end of the year,
برونز خيوساني: سؤال: أنت تتنحى عن عملك في نهاية هذه السنة،
after 10 years.
بعد 10 سنوات،
If you look back at 2005,
إذا رجعت بالوقت إلى العام 2005
when you entered that office for the first time, what do you see?
عندما دخلت إلى ذلك المكتب، ما الذي رأيته؟
AG: Well, look:
أنطونيو غيتراس: حسنا، انظر:
In 2005, we were helping one million people go back home
في سنة 2005، ساعدنا مليون شخص في العودة إلى ديارهم
in safety and dignity, because conflicts had ended.
في أمان مع حفظ كرامتهم، بسبب انتهاء الصراعات.
Last year, we helped 124,000.
في السنة الماضية، ساعدنا 124.000
In 2005, we had about 38 million people displaced by conflict in the world.
في سنة 2005، كان لدينا ما يقارب 38 مليون نازح جراء النزاعات بالعالم.
Today, we have more than 60 million.
اليوم، لدينا أكثر من 60 مليون.
At that time, we had had, recently,
في ذلك الوقت، كانت لدينا، مؤخرا،
some conflicts that were solved.
بعض النزاعات التي تم حلّها.
Now, we see a multiplication of new conflicts
حاليّا، نشهد تضاعف نزاعات جديدة
and the old conflicts never died:
والنزاعات القديمة لم تختفي بعد:
Afghanistan, Somalia, Democratic Republic of Congo.
أفغانستان والصومال وجمهورية الكونغو الديمقراطية.
It is clear that the world today is much more dangerous than it was.
من الواضح أن العالم اليوم أصبح أكثر خطورة مما كان عليه من قبل.
It is clear that the capacity of the international community
من الواضح أن قدرة المجتمع الدولي
to prevent conflicts and to timely solve them,
لمنع النزاعات وحلّهم في الوقت المناسب،
is, unfortunately, much worse than what it was 10 years ago.
أسوء للأسف مما كانت عليه خلال العشر السنوات الفائتة
There are no clear power relations in the world,
لا توجد علاقات واضحة للقوة في العالم،
no global governance mechanisms that work,
لا توجد آليات حوكمة عالمية تعمل بشكل جيد،
which means that we live in a situation
مما يعني أننا سنعيش في وضعية
where impunity and unpredictability tend to prevail, and that means
حيث يُهيمن الإفلات من العقاب وعدم القدرة على التنبؤ وهو ما يعني
that more and more people suffer,
معاناة أشخاص أكثر فأكثر،
namely those that are displaced by conflicts.
تحديداً أولئك النازحين بسبب النزاعات.
BG: It's a tradition in American politics
برونز خيوساني: إنها عادة في السياسة الامريكية
that when a President leaves the Oval Office for the last time,
عندما يغادر الرئيس المكتب البيضاوي للمرة الأخيرة،
he leaves a handwritten note on the desk for his successor
يترك مذكرة مكتوبة بخط يده على المكتب لخليفته
that walks in a couple of hours later.
الذي سيأتي بضع ساعات بعد رحيله.
If you had to write such a note to your successor, Filippo Grandi,
إذا كان عليك كتابة مثل هذه المذكرة لخليفتك، فيليبو غراندي،
what would you write?
ما الذي ستكتبه؟
AG: Well, I don't think I would write any message.
أنطونيو غيتراس: لا أعتقد بأنني سأكتب أي رسالة.
You know, one of the terrible things when one leaves an office
كما تعرف، أحد الأشياء السيئة عندما تغادر مكتبك
is to try to become the backseat driver,
هي محاولة أن تصبح في المقعد الخلفي للسائق،
always telling the new one what to do.
وتلقين الشخص الجديد ما عليه القيام به.
So that, I will not do.
إذن أنا لن اقوم بذلك.
If I had to say something to him,
إذا كان علي أن أقول له شيئا،
it would be, "Be yourself, and do your best."
سيكون التالي: "كن كما أنت، وابذل قصارى جهدك."
BG: Commissioner, thank you for the job you do.
برونز خيوساني: سيدي المفوض شكرا على الوظيفة التي تقوم بها.
Thank you for coming to TED.
شكرا لك لالتحاقك بتيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)